A Guide to the Edgar Wilson Nye ["Bill Nye"] Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7949-b
Edgar Wilson Nye ["Bill Nye"] Collection 1870-1900
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7949-b
27 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 1963 Dec 17 ] 1966 Jul 7
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Short Story: " An Unfinished Poem ", 1870; AMsS, 3 p.
  - " A Father's Letter to his Son ", 1893; AMsS, 11 p.
    [Includes book dealer's note.]
  - " Pall Mall St. ", 1894 Jan 12; AMsS, 8 p.
    [Signed Wm. Pauncefoot Nye.]
  - Poem beginning "The autumn leaves is falling.. .", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [For Miss May Smillie. ]
  - Beginning, "This is a reading from one of my unpublished works.. .", n. d.; AMsS, 5 p.
    [Includes typed transcript; gives account of the first money he ever earned and a visit to the circus.]
  - " The Autobiography of a Justice of the Peace ", n. d.; AMs, 3 p.
    [Includes pencil notation "Regular galley matter follows here" in an unknown hand.]
- Letters
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Leon Meare, 1882 Sep 17; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Encloses "Unfinished Poem" in letter; mentions Mr. [Roshacher].]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Frank Hatton, 1884 Oct 15; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    [Includes typewritten dealer's comment and original pen and ink drawing by Nye; as former postmaster of Laramie, he congratulates him on appointment as United States Postmaster General.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to "Friend Scott", 1885 Oct 17; ALS, 3 p.
    [Includes dealer's note; hopes to meet him in person on Nye's upcoming trip to Boston, having been acquainted with him for years in spirit only; accepts Scott's invitation to help him "destroy a chicken"; says he will stop on the way to Boston to deliver a lecture in Altoona, Pennsylvania; mentions his uncle, B. S. Nye. ]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Samuel Sidney McClure, 1885 Aug 28; ALS, 3 p.
    [Includes small magazine photo of Nye; indicates his readiness to do all his humorous writing for McClure's syndicate; suggests that it would be more profitable for both the writer and the paper; says that copyright would prevent his articles from being "stolen" by other papers as frequently is the case now.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Samuel Sidney McClure, 1885 Oct 21; ALS, 2 p.
    [Agrees to write exclusively for the syndicate if conditions can be met, starting with $60 per week; asks the publisher to pay him whatever is fair for the material that has already been published.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to James Newton Matthews, 1887 Dec 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Relates how James Whitcomb Riley"secured the Metropolitan Pelt at the Author's Reading"; says Riley was not given a chance but was very convincing in introducing his own style of humor; states that the audience, press, as well as the critics were enthusiastic.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Walter Hugh McDougall, 1889 May 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Includes typewritten dealer's note; begins "Sir. You cannot scare me with your hot words," and ends "I do not seek a quarrel but the widows and orphans of those who has monkeyed with me agree that I am no slouch. Defiantly yours."]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Mr. Chambers, 1889 Aug 28; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends a piece that appeared in the
    Journalist
    and asks him to paste it in his scrapbook.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to John R. Clements, 1890 Sep 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Informs him that from now on he intends to publish his own books, starting with an Almanac for 1891.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to "My dear Edward", 1890 Dec 17; ALS, 4 p.
    [Includes original pen and ink self-portrait caricature waving goodbye to ships; humorously commiserates with a friend who has shattered a foot; relates at length his own experience with a broken leg; says his after-dinner speeches at club have become much better since he took to drinking goat's milk and Vichy; says the speeches aren't as witty as before, but they read better in the papers.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to "My dear fellow", 1890 Dec 17; ALS, 1 p.
    [Includes pen and ink self-portrait at top of page; informs him that he will come to the Author's Club; gladly accepts offer to spend the night at his home.]
  - Edgar Wilson ["Bill Nye"] Nye to Mr. Kemble, 1891 Jan 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [Looks forward to meeting him at the Emporium of Major James B. Pond; agrees to look at a manuscript with Kemble.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to "Dear Sir", 1891 Sep; ALS (facsimile), 1 p.
    [Announces opening of his new play
    The Cadi
    on September 21, 1891, at the Union Square Theater in New York City; declares that the expense for the production would be appalling to him had he to furnish the money himself; says the play relates to his own experience as a Justice of the Peace on the frontier.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Samuel Sidney McClure, 1893 Jul 8; ALS, 1 p.
    [Turns down a request to do an interview "between me and myself" for the paper; claims that readers would not be interested and that he is pressed for time; suggest instead an interview between James Whitcomb Riley and himself.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to "Dear Boy", 1895 Nov 21; ALS, 5 p.
    [Humorous description of an accident he and his wife had.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to B. G. Brown, 1895 Jul 31; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for a letter expressing regard and generous applause.]
  - "Doe" to "My dear Harry", 1900 Nov 13; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends on request an old Bill Nye letter dealing with an injured foot; announces a visit to Philadelphia where he hopes to see Harry; promised letter is probably to "My dear Edward" from 1890 December 17.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to "Dear Leon", n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Extends an invitation to visit him at his home.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to unknown, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Fragment praising the music of his friend [Richard] Wagner, stating that it is much better than it sounds; sends James Whitcomb Riley's address.]
  - Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] to Richard Watson Gilder, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Assures him of his readiness to write for him again.]
- Photographs and prints
  - Four magazine photos on one page of Edgar Wilson Nye["Bill Nye"] at ages 20, 28, and at the present day, Photos
    [Includes 5 photos of George Washington Cable on verso.]